Is this better?
People can hear me in the back.
OK, let's get started.
Last week I was at a conference, so hopefully you had fun with Rahul, who is my 25th PhD graduate,
and he's doing outstanding work on micro architecture.
Did it all go well?
OK, great.
Yeah.
Today we're going to continue what he started and we're going to cover perhaps one of the most
fascinating topics that make pipeline processors work, which is predicting branches.
We covered some of this when we talked about pipelining, but we're going to go into methods that are
much more sophisticated, and existing processors employ even more sophisticated methods than what
we're going to describe toward the end, hybrids of multiple different types of branch predictors.
And this is one thing that makes the processor successful because you need to keep the pipeline full
and flowing, right?
If you have branches control flow instructions, this disrupts the control, disrupts the flow of
instructions, the pipeline.
And as a result, you may not actually get useful instructions to the pipeline if you predict the
branch wrong, for example.
So I will cover that.
You've seen this concept before, so I'm going to skip one of the early parts because these are
background.
OK.
So we have discussed essentially a lot of micro architecture recently.
We're going to end this tomorrow, hopefully.
Let's see how Long Branch prediction will go today.
We'll still cover some micro architecture, but we're also going to look into execution models like
VLIW and Systolic Erase tomorrow.
So branch prediction is the last topic in classical micro architecture, but then we'll also talk
about memory hierarchy.
So at this part of the course, these are some readings.
Hopefully you guys are doing some readings.
These are very good readings in my view to think about.
Today.
We're going to cover combining branch predictors in part, and I'm going to talk about the branch
predictor that's employed in some high performance processes like the Alpha 21 to 64.
We've also released some optional lectures, partly because we cover the data flow graph construction
on this older one and also you will cover this in your homeworks, optional homeworks, but this
there's a dynamic version of it.
If you're given the state of an out of order execution machine, the register alias table and the
reservation stations, you can reverse engineer.
The instructions that are currently in the machine or at least the data flow graph you can reverse
engineer.
You should be able to reverse engineer because it's a restricted data flow machine, right?
That's that that proves that this a restricted data flow.
And you may be able to reverse engineer the exact ordering of the instructions potentially you, but
you may not be able to also.
So these are some exercise that we have in homeworks and these are really great exam questions, if
you know what I mean.
I like reverse engineering questions because if you are presented with something and if you can
reverse engineer what's going on, that's likely tells you that you have understood the subject
really well.
It's not a forward engineering question.
A forward engineering question tends to be easier, but reverse engineering really truly requires you
to understand what's going on in the system potentially.
OK, so that's the and also this lecture is a bit easier to follow online because I use the mouse.
I think Rahul being being a young teacher, maybe they didn't use the mouse as much, but I learned
this also similarly he did.
OK, so we have another optional lecture.
This is load store handling.
This is probably the most complicated part of an out of order processor today.
It's a very short lecture, but hopefully it will give you the complexity of the processors that we
have today, but I'll let you study it.
OK, So these are different ways of handling control dependences.
We've covered some of them and today's focus is going to be on branch prediction, which we start
last time and we motivated the problem last time with an example.
In this example, we have a 20 stage pipeline processor, 5 white superscalar processor, 5 white
pitch.
And we discussed this.
Essentially, how long does it take to fetch 500 instructions with some assumptions, right?
Do you remember this?
We're assuming one out of five instructions a branch, and each five instruction block ends with a
branch, Pretty regular.
Now, if you have 100% accuracy, of course, it takes only 100 cycles and I your IPC would be 5
instructions per cycle.
But if you have 90% accuracy, you're quickly down to an IPC of five over three 1.6 bar and two 100%
extra instructions that you fetch, right?
If your accuracy is 60%, you're fetching 800% extra instructions than you really need.
So this shows you the importance of the problem.
And this problem becomes worse as N becomes larger and as W becomes larger, because you're wasting a
lot more slots with a given mispredicted branch, both with N&W.
You can think of this as a box with dimensions N&W and you waste n * W instruction slots if you
actually mispredict the branch, right?
OK, so you want to reduce the frequency of mispredictions basically, and that's what we're going to
try to do.
So branch prediction this is, I'll go through this relatively quickly because you've seen this.
Essentially you predict the next instruction to fetch instead of stalling.
Stalling is a bad idea even with a very short pipeline.
As you, as you, as you see over here, 5 stage pipeline, if you predict the next instruction to
fetch, you can keep the pipeline full.
OK, we can improve performance.
Of course, if you mispredict, then you need to redirect the fetch to the correct engine after
flashing the correct program counter after flashing the incorrect instructions, then we've seen
that also.
So I'll not go through that.
And we said that the easiest method is predicting next program counter to be PC Plus an increment.
Increment is the size of the instruction.
And in MIPS, it's nice, it's four.
In some other ISA, size of the instruction depends on the instruction.
As a result, you cannot know the size before you decode the instruction.
So immediately you have a problem, right?
You need to figure out the next PC even when you want to.
The next PC equals PC Plus instruction size.
Your ISA determines how well you can do it.
If your instructions are regular, all of them are 4 bytes, then it's easy.
OK, so X86 for example.
A instruction can be anywhere between 1 to 16, maybe even 17 these days.
Bytes.
And in order to predict the next instruction, you need to predict the size of the instruction also.
OK, so it's a harder problem if your ISA doesn't have same size instructions.
Makes sense.
It's interesting.
So this part of the processor is actually pretty complicated because of this sort of issues,
especially an X86 processor.
So we also talked about how can you make this more effective.
You can do this by maximising the chances that the next sequential instruction is the next
instruction to be executed.
You can do this in software.
There's a beautiful paper in PLDI that a lot of compilers today use.
If you actually do this sort of prediction, they basically profile the code and they try to lay out
the code such that the next sequential instruction is the next likely instruction.
That's the idea.
You can also do this in hardware.
Maybe we will talk about it, maybe not, but their hardware structures that try to do essentially the
same thing in hardware, What I just described is called the trace cache and that exists in some
processors.
OK, I'll not go through this.
We discussed this last time.
Now let's go into a more enhanced branch prediction.
We're going to look at some algorithms to predict branches.
So the general idea is really we want to predict the next fetch address that the.
Cluster is going to fetch from in the next cycle immediately next cycle so that we don't have any
wasted cycles on a correct prediction, right?
And ideally we want to get 100% correct predictions.
This requires actually three things to be predicted at the fetch stage.
1 is whether the fetched instructions are branch.
That's also a problem, right?
And the direction of the branch, assuming it's a conditional branch.
We're going to focus on conditional branches.
Indirect branches are more complicated, but we're not going to talk about them right now.
There are some backup slides.
If it's a conditional branch, what is the direction taken or not taken, essentially, And the target
address of the branch, assuming the branch is taken.
So you need to predict all three of these things, right?
And if the branch is not taken, you need to predict the next instruction, next sequential
instructions address.
And in that case, it may be easy if your ISA has fixed instruction sizes, it's harder if your ISA
has variable instruction sizes.
So I'm going to, I'm not going to talk about that part as much from now on.
But let's let's talk about branch target address.
How do you predict it?
And the same structure that is used to predict the branch target address actually can be used to
predict whether the fetched instructions are branch.
And the idea.
The observation that enables this is that target address of a branch of a conditional branch.
Direct branch remains the same across dynamic instances.
So you for example calculate the target address using PC Plus some offset.
The program counter of the branch remains the same.
Offset remains the same, so your target address is always the same.
This is a direct branch.
Indirect branches can obtain the target program counter as a register plus some offset.
In that case, that's an indirect branch, and we're not going to deal with that right now, right?
But for a direct branch where target is PC Plus some offset, what you can do is the first time you
execute the branch, you store the target address in a buffer in a structure.
We're going to call this the branch target address cache or branch target buffer, and you can access
this with the program counter.
For each program counter, you have a target address.
Think about a table like that, and when you actually see the program counter again, you index that
table and get the target address without waiting to execute the branch.
That's the idea we have.
We'll have the structure and the fetch stage take that table called branch target buffer.
IBM called this branch target address cache, but it's essentially BTBI guess has taken off as a
word.
OK, so this is how our fetch stage going to be.
Essentially we will need a bTB cache or buffer of target addresses.
Don't worry about the cache terminology right now.
You'll see caches a lot when we talk about processor.
Let me talk about memory systems.
And the structure is going to be essentially the same, but you don't need to know exactly how this
is organised right now.
All you need to know is you index it using program counter and assuming you have stored an associate
target address with that program counter, you will get the target address that you stored.
Otherwise you will get nothing out of it.
OK and then there's a direction projector that says whether the branch should be predicted as taken
or not taken using the program counter, meaning address of the current branch or current
instruction.
We're going to index into the cache of target addresses.
It'll give us 2 signals.
1 is whether we hit, whether we have something for that program counter.
And if we have, if we do have something, then the target address is the target address that's branch
calculated the previous time it executed.
OK.
And then we also index using the program counter.
We're going to make this more complicated later on.
A direction predictor and the direction predictor will predict whether the branch is taken or not
taken.
Right now if the branch is taken and if the bTB provides us a hit, then the next next fetch address
is taken from the bTB as a target address.
If the branch is taken, predicted taken.
I should say, if the direction predictor predicts the branch has taken and if the bTB doesn't have a
target address, meaning this is a 0, you will see that PC Plus instruction size is selected as the
next fetch address.
PC Plus 4IN MIPS, if the branch is predicted not taken, then it doesn't matter whether you hit or
miss over here because of this and gate, then PC Plus instruction size again select as the next
fetch address.
So this is the logic that we have in the front end.
This will become more complicated as you will see soon, but that's the idea.
Hopefully it makes sense, right?
You've seen all components before.
Now the question is, of course, how do we build this direction predictor?
And people have invested a lot of effort to make this as accurate as possible.
Now if you if you make this direction predictor more complicated, it's going to affect your cycle
time, right?
Remember, we want to get this prediction.
In one cycle, so I said while we're accessing also a concurrently, which is not shown here, you're
also concurrently accessing the instruction memory or instruction cache.
As we will see it, you're fetching the instruction, you're also predicting what is the next
instruction to fetch, and you want to do this within the same cycle.
If it takes too long to determine the direction predictor, like whether you want to predict taken or
not taken, then you can actually extend the clock cycle time and fetch stage can easily extend the
clock cycle time.
Modern branch predictors take multiple cycles to provide predictions, as we will hopefully see
toward the end of this lecture.
So it's not an easy part of the machine to design.
OK, remember the next fetch address actually goes back into and gets written into the program
counter, right?
There's a loop over here.
OK, so a more sophisticated dredge prediction, which will come, does something like this.
We're actually going to use global branches too.
For example, we're going to put more context.
Right now, this may look like magic, but we're going to use more context of the program to decide
whether the branch will be taken, predicted, taken or not taken not.
Instead of using just the program counter, we're going to use which direction earlier branches went.
This called the global history of branches, because that actually has good correlation.
People have found out with the prediction that you're going to make for the current branch and we
will motivate why this is the case.
This is because of how programs behave.
Branches are not independent of each other.
They have, they are correlated because of data dependencies, because of code dependencies, etcetera.
And this, this is a global history predictor basically.
So the structure is essential the same except how you decide whether the branch is predicted is
taken or not taken is different, right?
Direction prediction is different, basically.
OK, we're going to make it more sophisticated.
So let's go back to these three things to be predicted.
We wanted to predict these three things.
The third one, meaning branch target address, can be accomplished using a bTB.
Remember the target address computed last time the branch was executed.
OK, so that's easy.
We solved it with some hardware.
This is a hardware structure.
The first one can also be accomplished using a bTB.
If the bTB provides a target address for the program counter, then it must be a branch, right?
It's a one to one mapping basically program counter to target address, OK.
There are other ways of doing this actually, which were employed in some processors in the past.
You have some partial decode information associated with a program counter that says basically a
single bit associated with each program counter that says whether or not it's a branch, right?
You could also do that partially decode instruction.
OK, Second one is what we're going to be concerned about.
How do we do?
How do you predict the direction?
Right?
So there are many branch prediction schemes that people have developed.
This is actually a fascinating area that requires even more creativity right now.
Some of them are compile time, which we will start with.
These are static mechanisms.
Some of them are at least the more sophisticated and more successful ones are the runtime
mechanisms.
You've already seen some of these, right?
Always not taken, for example, and we're going to see more sophisticated ones.
Hopefully we'll get some time to cover advanced algorithms like machine learning, the simple machine
learning algorithm like perceptrons, and also a geometric history length predictors, which are
actually used in real processors today.
Usually a lot of processors today use some of these things combined with advanced algorithms because
advanced algorithms take longer.
If you can actually predict a branch with a simple algorithm, it's much better to do so because
you're not wasting space in the advanced algorithms hardware budget, right?
That's the idea over here.
So existing processors have sophisticated branch predictors that have multiple different types of
prediction algorithms inside them.
OK, sounds good.
So let's start with compile time static branch prediction.
I'm going to cover these relatively quickly.
We've seen always not taken.
This is the simplest thing you can do because you don't need to predict the target address, right?
You always predict not taken.
So next, fetch address is always PC Plus instruction size.
Then your instruction size is constant, it's even easier.
This is simple to implement.
There is no need for a bTB, no direction prediction, no need to identify a branch.
You're basically doing business as usual, which is a control flow instruction is no different from a
non control flow instruction in the way you treat it in the fetch engine.
OK, now the downsides.
Of course this is pretty low accuracy, 30 to 40% accuracy and I don't have even have that picture
right.
We, we went down to 60% and with 60% we're still fetching 800% more instructions.
If you go down to 30% accuracy, not so good.
Of course you can optimise this compiler can layout code such that the likely path is the not taken
path.
It gives you a more effective prediction accuracy, but if you remember that discussion, that's also
unfortunately dependent on the information that the compiler has.
What if the compiler's information is not representative?
When the program is running, the compiler may say, oh, this is the likely path, but in real
execution with the real input sets, the other path may be the likely path.
So the compiler actually optimises the code in the wrong way, right?
So your accuracy becomes worse in that case.
So it's called the profile input set representativeness problem.
It's always an issue whenever you enable the compiler to make some decisions, static decisions,
because your dynamic program behaviour is very different from what the compiler sees statically.
Yes.
Is miss predicting a branch worse than installment?
Should we resolve the address or are they the same?
They're essentially the same, yeah.
Basically, you miss predicting a branch, you flush all of the pipeline stages and then you reload
the PC.
They may potentially be worse, but people don't do that design.
They try design to make sure that mispredicting is the same as stalling.
That's a good question, though there may be some no answers and some different architectures.
OK so people have developed always taken predictors.
Again, this is compile time static, meaning you don't change your direction.
Prediction is static right?
There is no direction predictor that's needed for this.
You're always predicting as taken.
You get better accuracy because most branches are taken.
Actually it turns out the reason is most branches are loop branches and loops tend to be executed
more than not.
You don't execute a loop only once and then get after it.
Usually you execute a loop 3 times.
Let's say in many application you want to execute the loop 1,000,000 times.
We're going to talk about that actually soon.
OK, so backward branches, loop branches are usually taken and backward branch is a branch that has
target address lower than the branch PC It's actually a loop branch that that loops into the
program, right?
You iterate over loop, for example, you're adding two arrays.
You keep doing it for every index and there's a branch that says go do it for the next one, go do it
for the next one, go to the next one.
So we're going to see these like backward benches too.
So people have looked at this and said, OK, if this is the case, why don't we actually design
another static prediction mechanism where if the branch is backward, we predicted as taken and if
the branch is forward, meaning not a loop branch, we predict it as not taken.
And it turns out this is better than these always taken and always not taken mechanism because it
takes into account the behaviour of loop branches better and it's gets better accuracy in the
forward branches that are not loop branches.
That's the heuristic that we have, OK?
That's the idea basically, right?
This is still static because it's really whether a branch is backward or forward, whether it goes
back in the code or forward in the code is a characteristic of the branch itself of the static
code, right?
It's not a static.
It doesn't change based on the dynamic instance of the branch, right?
OK, but it's more complicated.
Of course you need to decide which branch is backward and forward, and you need to have a bTB for
these two always taken and backward taken forward not taken mechanisms.
OK, so these are simple static prediction mechanisms, but they're also more sophisticated static
branch prediction mechanisms that could be profile based, meaning the compiler can profile the code
and decide for each branch how it should predict, how it should, how it should be predicted.
Now we're going to go to per branch mechanisms.
You would compile the terms of likely direction for each branch using a profile round and encodes
that direction as a hint bit in the branch instruction format.
For each branch instruction format, there's a bit that says, which is the likely direction of the
branch.
And the compiler sets this bit by running the program using some input sets for however many times,
right, there's somebody who decides that and the compiler says, oh, this branch is likely taken in
all of the data sets that I've seen, so I'm going to encode as likely taken.
This branch is likely not taken, So for every branch you can have a separate prediction.
So that's the upside over here, per branch prediction, it's more accurate than the schemes in the
previous slide because they're not per branch, they're global, based on categories of branches or
all branches.
So this is accurate if profiles representative of course, right, If what the compiler sees is
similar to what the runtime behaviour of the program is.
The downside of course is this requires hint bits in the instruction format.
The good news is it's only one bit.
Hopefully not too bad.
Basically, now the accuracy depends on the dynamic branch behaviour.
For example, if your dynamic behaviour branch behaviour looks like this 50% taken, 50% not taken
either with this pattern or with this pattern, you get 50% accuracy because the compiler cannot
encode the fact that you're changing behaviour at some point, right?
It can.
It can encode only One Direction as a likely direction.
So 50% is very bad because both directions are likely or both directions are equally unlikely,
right?
OK, so these branches are tough.
So accuracy also depends on the representative.
Because of profile inputs that as we discussed for example here, the branch is likely taken 90% of
the time the compiler, if it has good information, it'll get 90% accuracy right?
It'll encode things the hint bit as one meaning taken.
If the compiler has bad information or not representative information of the dynamic behaviour the
compiler may get, the compiler may encode this branch as not likely or not taken, like not taken,
and as a result you get 10% accuracy.
That's the danger of compiler based mechanisms.
But if you had a dynamic mechanism, you can probably predict this very easily as we will see, right?
OK, so that's profile based.
People have also developed program based mechanisms.
This is a beautiful paper by Thomas Bolan and Jim Lehr's Branch Prediction for Free.
The idea in this paper is very nice.
It's very hard to make it work in practice I think, especially today, but I'll give you the idea.
The idea is to not use profile, but use heuristics by ident, by analysing the program to decide what
is the likely direction each branch would take.
So what are these things?
What are these heuristics?
So you can analyse the program, That's called program analysis basically and look at for some op
codes for example, and if the branch op code is branch less than or equal to 0, you predict it as
not taken.
Why?
Because based on some analysis they did these faults figured out.
Negative integers are used as error values in many programs and BLEZ branch less than or equal to 0
checks an error value.
And usually you don't get errors.
And I guess usually in the program, if you get errors, you'll do something else anyway, so you
predict that's not taken.
So that's the idea basically.
It's more intuitive.
It can be based on data also, but not necessarily on a particular run of a program That's directly
impacting the direction prediction.
Another loop heuristic, for example, these folks decide that you predict a branch guarding a loop.
Execution is taken, meaning execute the loop.
There's a branch.
If some condition then execute a big loop, usually that branch is taken, meaning usually execute the
loop.
Because programs usually execute based on loops.
That's the idea again, right?
You can do the statistical of course, right?
For example, comparing 2 pointers, you predict the pointers as not equal, because that's the
likelihood of that is very low.
Comparing 2 floating point numbers, again you predict that as not equal.
You should never do this by the way in your program, but there may be some cases.
I guess you predict not equal, so hopefully you get the idea right and you can come up with hundreds
of heuristics like this and this paper does maybe 20 or so.
The upside is this doesn't require profile, it's really program analysis based.
The downside is heuristics might not be representative or very good.
It requires compiler analysis and ISA support.
That's true for other static methods also that are not the simplest static methods.
And this paper shows that you can actually get 20% misprediction rate at the time in 1993 using
these methods, which actually pretty impressive, I would say.
OK, but that's an idea, tough to make it work in modern processors because of the complexity of the
code.
OK.
There's also another step, branch prediction mechanism that relies on the programmer that makes life
harder for the programmer, but that also takes advantage of the programmer's understanding of the
code potentially, right?
So the idea is to have the programmer decide, provide the statically predicted direction for each
branch or for branches where they know information about.
And you do this via pragmas in the programming language that qualify the branches likely taken
versus likely not taken.
Pragma is essentially an indication of something in the program.
I'm going to talk about that.
So each branch, the programmer basically the programmer sets that hint bit inside the branch.
So the upside is this doesn't require profiling or program analysis.
And programmer may know that some branches behave in will behave in some way and they may know their
program better than other analysis techniques, right?
They know because they have semantic information about what they're doing in the program.
They may be checking for an error that they know is not going to happen anytime, but they have to
check for that error to guarantee correctness of the program, right?
And this may not be easy to figure out for via program analysis.
Yes, you can use heuristics like what we discussed, but programmer may know for sure the semantic
context of the branch.
OK.
Of course the downside is this now requires programming language compiler and ISA support all of
them.
But this sort of techniques are actually good to think about going into the future, especially if
you have a good AI programmer, for example, maybe they can do these things nicely over time, OK.
Outside, of course, this burdens the programmer, right?
If you burden the programmer, this is not easy to adopt in general.
OK, so what's pragmas?
Pragmas we've discussed, These are essentially keywords in the programming language that enable a
programmer to convey information to the lower levels of the hierarchy.
Transformation hierarchy, meaning to the ISA, to the compiler, to the hardware, essentially.
Have you ever used pragmas and code?
OK.
What kind of pragmas?
Parallelization maybe?
OK, OK.
OK.
I see.
Yeah, Yeah, I see.
OK.
I'm talking about more maybe finer grain pragmas.
But for example, these are some pragmas.
If likely X, this is a branch if X, instead of saying if X, you say if likely X.
Likely in this case indicates that that branch is likely taken, right?
If unlikely error, and that that unlikely indicates that unlikely.
That branch is like unlikely to be taken, likely to be not taken.
Basically meaning you don't execute the error code right in general.
So many other hints and optimisations can be enabled with pragmas, For example, whether a loop can
be paralysed.
A lot of people use this one today, actually.
For example, if you're doing open MP type of programming, you can have an open open MP parallel.
And this description from some version of the Open MP manual, it says the OEMP parallel directive
explicitly instructs the compiler to parallelise the chosen segment of code, right?
It's an explicit, explicit pragma that the compiler uses.
That's true for the likely and unlikely.
The compiler uses these to communicate to the branch instruction to set the bid in the branch
instruction appropriately.
OK, OK, so essentially we're getting to the end of static branch prediction.
We can also combine all of these previous techniques.
We can do profile based, program based, programmer based static prediction because for some branches
profile is good.
Maybe for some branches program based heuristics are good, for some branches programmer based is
better.
The difficulty is it becomes more complex to do this and you burden and sometimes you may not know
which one's better, right?
So I can combine all of these static techniques.
Unfortunately, there is a common disadvantage of all three techniques that we, I kind of, I kind of
adapt, I kind of hinted at, right?
Essentially you're picking only One Direction for a given branch.
What if that branch keeps changing that direct, changing its direction.
Take a not take and take a not take and take a not take, right?
None of these techniques that we described so far can adapt to dynamic changes in a given branches
behaviour.
Of course you can say that oh, I can have a dynamic compiler.
So once in a while I change, I re, I recompile the code dynamically automatically and I change the
hint bit in all of the branches.
Yes, it's possible to do that, but it's very difficult to do that at a very fine grain late.
What if a branch changes behaviour every execution?
Taken, not taken, take and not take and take and not take it.
You cannot possibly compile for that except without huge overheads.
So dynamic compiler essentially.
We've covered this in the past.
Actually it's a compiler that generates code at runtime.
Java JIT compiler for example, just in time compiler, common language runtime from Microsoft.
And we've seen the binary translator was a tattoo if you remember.
And NVIDIA has dynamic code optimised.
So these are actually very commonly used.
The idea is to figure out which parts of a code is executed often, using some mechanisms that
profile the code while the program is running, using some, using some hardware support for example,
and once in a while recompile the code so that you can actually optimise a code for the path that's
being executed most frequently.
So you can do that, and you can actually take advantage of that to improve branch prediction
accuracy.
But this comes at overheads in general because you need to compile dynamically.
OK, so now we're going to get to more sophisticated bench prediction, which is the runtime part.
No questions, let's keep going.
So when you predict a branch, you predict in the fetch stage and you resolve the branch in the
execute stage, right?
When you execute it, if the direction doesn't match the predicted direction, then you flash the
pipeline.
Yeah.
So whenever the branch is executed, yeah.
OK.
So the idea of dynamic branch prediction.
Is to predict branches based on dynamic information.
It's very simple, collected at runtime.
This is done with hardware.
Basically, you do it with some hardware support.
Let's talk about advanced and disadvantage, and then we're going to talk about some techniques.
Essentially, here you're predicting based on the history of the execution of branches.
You have more information, more context, which means that you should be able to adapt to dynamic
changes in each branch's behaviour, and we will see that there's no need for static profiling.
The input set represented in this problem goes away basically because you're dealing with what the
processor is executing at that time.
All of the data set is real.
It's not basically something you imagined that might happen.
This is disadvantage, of course, this is more complex.
This requires additional hardware, as we will see, and it will add more and more hardware over time.
OK, so let's start with the simplest of these predictors, which is the last time predictor.
It's kind of obvious, but the idea is to guess that the branch will take the same direction as its
last instance of execution.
You need to have a single bit per branch, in this case stored in the bTB for example, and this
indicates which direction the branch went last time it was executed.
OK, so if you look at this pattern of execution of branch, the 1st 10 times it's taken, the next 10
times it's not taken and then assume that it's going to go back to taken 10 times, not taken 10
times, and then it's going to go back to that.
Basically it's in a loop, it keeps executing in a loop and it's 10 times not taken and 10 times not
taken.
If you always predict the last time as the current prediction, for example, you will predict these
correctly.
You will mispredict this first end because it doesn't match the previous execution, right?
The previous execution is taken, the next execution is supposed to be not taken, but you will
mispredict this one.
And you will also mispredict this first T because the previous execution, assuming this executed
loop is, is not taken for that branch, but it's support, it's going to be taken.
So you'll mispredict this as N OK, so for these 20 instances of the same branch, you'll mispredict
twice whenever the branch changes direction.
So you get 90% accuracy, which is much nicer than 50% you would get with a static prediction
mechanism, right?
Sounds good.
Basically, the more generally, this always mispredicts the last iteration and the first iteration of
a loop branch, if you think about it.
Or you can think of it, whenever the branch changes direction because it's last time, it cannot
adapt beyond last time.
It doesn't have enough history.
OK, the accuracy for a loop with N iterations is n - 2 / n, which is what you see over here, 18 / 20
for example.
Now the good news is, if N is large, meaning you keep iterating over a very large loop, you get
almost 100% accuracy.
If N is small loop branches for loops with small N small number of iterations, you get very low
accuracy, in this case 0% accuracy, for example.
So this predictor doesn't do well if the branch changes direction every time, right?
Because you'll always predict what it did last time.
And unfortunately you'll get everything wrong over here, but we're going to fix that.
Yeah, this is clearly a predictable pattern, Yes.
Yeah, because the last time the branch was executed, it was not taken, right.
That's the reason.
Basically, you always keep a history of what was the last time this program counter, what happened
to what happened to this program counter branch at this program counter last time.
Oh, OK.
I see.
Yeah, yeah.
But that's a very good question.
Basically, we're going to talk about that.
You need to initialise that those bits to something and you may or may not be lucky.
Yeah, that's that depends on the initialisation.
That's very good.
This actually assumes that you are.
Yeah, I guess you may be correct.
But then, yeah, OK, in the long run you will go to n -, 2 / 2 N basically.
OK, So how do you implement this last time predictor?
Essentially, we have a program counter and the direction predictor has one bit.
It basically this one bit indicates whether the branch has taken last time, right?
Makes sense hopefully.
And the question is, of course, the size of the stretch direction predictor may be smaller than the
number of branches you have in the program.
So you need to hash into this direction predictor in some way index into the direction predictor.
So there are many design choices over here that we will not get into.
But if the size is huge, then it takes long to access.
If the size is small, you may have interference.
From other branches, right?
Because you need to hash into this index into it in some way, and some other branches may actually
interfere in the same entry.
OK, that's always a issue with branch prediction.
OK, this is another implementation of the last time predictor.
This is our program counter.
We're going to see this more when we talk about caches, so I'll go through this relatively quickly.
But the basic idea is you index the branch target buffer.
Oh, what happens here?
Now you index the branch target buffer with some bits of the program counter.
And you also store the tag which is really part of the program counter.
And if the tag matches, then you have the target for that particular program counter.
You also add one bit per each entry over here called the branch history table, which is really the
direction predictor.
So you can integrate the direction predictor inside the branch target buffer like this.
Instead of having just one target address per entry.
You also have a direction bit associated with the branch because you're using the PC program counter
to index into the bTB anyway, right?
And the rest is basically very similar to what I've shown you over here.
OK, we're going to cover this sort of structure a lot when we cover about caches, Cache will be
very, very similar to this.
You don't need to know this at this point, but hopefully you can empathise with what's going on a
little bit.
OK, so this is our state state machine per branch for a last time prediction.
There are two states 01 predict not taken, predict taken.
If the branch is actually taken, you stay in the predict taken state, right?
If the branch is actually not taken and you predict it's taken, you go back, you go to predict not
taken state and you stay in the state.
If you actually did the right thing, let's say, and you switch states.
If you look at this picture, you change your mind very quickly, basically with one single opposing
outcome than what you predicted.
You say, oh, OK, I did wrong.
Let me switch to being not taken as opposed to taken, right?
And then you can keep flip flopping, right?
Basically you don't have, let's say, hysteresis in your behaviour.
Do you guys know the concept of hysteresis?
For example, you design an air conditioning system, right?
And you decide to set the target temperature to 20°C.
You're at 20°C.
That's good.
The room heats up, it becomes 20.00001, and the system immediately starts cooling.
And then the temperature becomes 19.99999999, The system immediately becomes heating, starts
heating.
And the system keeps doing this forever.
It's basically oscillating and it's really terrible for a lot of things, a lot of reasons, including
health.
So this system doesn't have any hysteresis, right?
Hysteresis basically says you wait before you change your mind.
There is some slack in the system.
So normally you don't basically the, the, the a good air conditioning system doesn't really change
its mind so quickly.
It basically starts observing and if the temperature is really a little bit too high beyond the
threshold, then it starts cooling, right.
OK, so basically the same issue exists over here.
A last time predictor changes its prediction from taken to not taken or not taken to taken too
quickly.
I mean, sometimes it may be correct in doing so, but we can fix this problem with some simple
solution.
Even though the branch may be mostly taken or mostly not taken, basically it doesn't have a global
picture of the branch.
We're still not going to add a global picture here, but we're going to add hysteresis just like the
AC air conditioning that I described, add hysteresis to the predictor so that prediction does not
change on a single different outcome.
And the way we add hysteresis to a lot of predictors in computing is to add more bits.
Basically use more bits to track the history of predictions for a branch instead of a single bit,
right?
Two bits as opposed to one, or three bits as opposed to 1.
And go to different states that indicate different levels of takenness or not takenness.
OK, So for example, you can add 2 states each for taken or not taken instead of 1 state for each.
And whenever you change your mind, you go from let's say strongly taken state to weakly taken state.
You still predicting taken but you're you want to see another opposing outcome for example.
That's the idea.
Basically you can you can generalise this to end states.
So this is introduced in the Seminole paper by Jim Smith, who has also contributed a lot of other
things to computer architecture in 1981.
And this basically had a huge impact on how pipeline processors got designed.
So this is the idea.
Basically each branch is associated with a 2 bit counter or three bits.
One more bit provides hysteresis and a strong prediction does not change with one single different
outcome.
This is also called bimodal prediction.
I don't like this term, but that's it's got stuck a little bit.
Basically what this is what we're going to do.
For example if you have a 2 bit.
Saturating counter, we're going to saturate.
Two states are allocated to predicted taken and two states are allocated to predicted not taken.
You can see 01001011 over here, right?
And we're using saturating arithmetic, meaning you increment the counter and decrement the counter,
but there's a maximum value which is 11 and there's a minimum value that's 00.
You cannot decrement it below that, and you cannot increment it above this, right?
That's why it's called saturating arithmetic.
And the idea is if the counter state is in this predicted taken, strongly predicted taken, and the
branch is actually not taken, you discovered that by executing the branch, you go into another
predicted taken state first before switching your mind.
And this is a weekly taken state.
If at that point the branch is actually not taken again in that instance, then you switch your mind,
right?
Then you go to a predicted not taken state that's weakly predicted, not taken.
So that's basically the implementation of hysteresis using a counter based mechanism.
And it's very low cost.
You have two bits as opposed to 1.
You can argue that you're doubling the cost, of course that's true.
But two bits is not bad.
We're going to see some predictors that has huge budgets.
For example, this thing, even though it's old, has huge branch predictors.
Some of the best branch predictors are inside this thing.
OK, anyway, so I already said this, but you have strongly taken and weakly taken, strongly take, not
taken, and weakly not taken states.
OK, so how do you implement this?
You essentially need a 2 bit counter associated with each branch and also a counter increment
decrement logic, right?
Now let's take a look at the accuracy of this, right?
So let's take a look at a branch that has N iterations, a loop branch with N iterations.
It'll only make a mistake once, right?
Assuming countries initialise the weekly take.
So let's go back your question over here.
So if you assume weekly taken, the first instance will become strongly taken and you'll become
strongly taken in all of these instances.
And then you'll predict this branch instance as taken.
You'll be incorrect because this is really not taken, right?
But then you'll go to a state that's weekly taken.
So the next instance when you go back over here, you'll predict it correct again.
So this is assuming you're initialized to weekly taken.
If you're weekly not taken, you can do the analysis yourself and you're going to do this in your
homework and maybe in the exam, who knows?
But the good news over here is we have 95% accuracy, right?
We reduced it from 90%, increase it from 90%.
And if you look over here, unfortunately, we're still at 50% accuracy.
We didn't fix this problem even though there's also a good nicely predictable, right?
So this works nicely.
If the branch doesn't change its behaviour that much, we're going to develop other techniques to fix
this problem because this is really easily predictable, right?
If you actually keep track of the branch's history in the past, we're going to call this a local
history predictor.
You can get this perfectly correct also in the long run.
So the upside is we get better prediction accuracy.
It's not n - 2 / N, it's n -, 1 / N now, but more hardware cost.
But the counter can be part of the bTB entry as usual.
OK, let's talk about this now.
If people have figured out that this gives you 85 to 90% accuracy for many programs, that's what the
paper, Jim Smith's paper from 1981 showed, for example, and essentially all processors immediately
adopted this idea.
Just an example of academic research having almost immediate impact.
I've been very happy about the research that we do.
Also, you can have immediate impact in products, but this is not good enough basically.
Basically, you know the branch problem, right?
Let's take a look at this.
80% accuracy with 80% accuracy with the same set up, your IPC is only one as opposed to 5, right?
And you're fetching 8 four 100% extractions with 85%.
Your IPC is 1.25 and you're fetching 300% extra instructions.
So basically, we're not there.
Then the question is, what do you do?
Right.
Let me introduce the high level over here and then we're going to take a break.
So the next Seminole paper came ten years after this.
This is a paper from my PhD advisor, Yael Pat.
He and his students at the time did a lot of great research.
They also were the ones who actually enabled auto ward execution to make work in real life by
enabling precise exceptions to be used together with out of order execution.
A lot of along with a lot of other things that we didn't discuss.
But one of the issues that they faced in that micro architecture is branch prediction becomes a much
bigger problem if you have a deeper wider out of order execution machine.
You need to fill the machine with correct instructions, otherwise you're executing useless stuff.
So they basically worked on how to make branch prediction much better.
And they wrote this paper in 1991, it got immediately adopted also to Intel Pentium Pro as we will
discuss, which is the most first, most successful auto order execution machine of its time.
So there are two realisations basically last time and two bit counter predictors exploit last time
predictability, but they don't exploit some other types of predictability that are relatively easy
to exploit if you know how to design the right hardware.
And 1st predictability is a branch's outcome can be correlated with other branches outcomes.
This is actually probably the biggest leap over here.
Use other branches outcomes to predict the current branch's outcome, right?
This is called global branch correlation and all existing processors use this.
And the second realisation is that a branch's outcome can be correlated with past outcomes of the
same branch other than the outcome of the branch last time it was executed.
This may be commuted, but you're looking at last time predictability, right?
But if you go back over here, this picture, last time doesn't help you, right?
Because last time is changing.
Why not look at a more longer history that's local to that branch?
Then you can predict that much better, right?
So I can basically identify patterns much better if you actually go back and have a longer history,
it's called the local branch correlation or local history predictors.
This also employed in the best processors, let's say, because it's so good to do.
OK, so let's take a break over here.
We're going to be back at 1515, sorry.
And then we'll continue with global and local correlation.
Now we'll see how it's implemented, because implementation is really important over here.
Better now.
OK, so let's continue now.
Now we're going to go into much more exciting techniques and these are all in your processors.
That's the fascinating part.
Well, everything we discussed in your processors actually so far out of order execution.
Well, we'll go into deeper and deeper things.
Sometimes people think branch prediction is like black magic, you know, why does it work?
And there are a lot of things actually that you need to tune to make it work.
There's partly tuning, but there's a lot of insight into these mechanisms also, right?
They're really exploiting the program behaviour.
OK, let's start with the global branch correlation, the first insight in this 1991 paper.
And the idea is this basically recently executed branch outcomes and the execution path are
correlated with the outcome of the next branch or the current, the current branch that you're
trying to predict, right?
That's the idea.
For example, you can look at this code and you can clearly say that the second branch's outcome will
be correlated with the first one, right?
If the first branch is not taken, second is also not taken.
That sounds good.
Now.
Now I can use this for my prediction, right?
You can also look at this code and this code.
If the first branch is taken, the second is definitely not taken, right?
So these are good things to exploit, potentially to predict later branches based on the outcome of
previous branches.
OK, you can convince yourself these are different kinds of structures.
There are different reasons why the second is not taken if the first is taken.
But in the end it boils down to the fact that if the first branch is T, the next branch should be N,
right?
That's the idea.
You should predict the next branch is N OK, a bit more complicated here.
If the there are three branches yz and X.
If Y&Z are both taken, then X is also taken.
If Y or Z are not taken, then X is also not taken.
Right?
Basically if you see TT then X should be T If you see any N then X should be N.
Now we can design A predictor that predicts based on the history of these branches, right?
That's the idea.
Another one over here.
This was a very famous workload and spec workloads that people used to evaluate microprocessors with
at the time.
That's where people used to compete, right?
Today, these are AI workloads.
Of course, at that time there were some set of workloads, Standard Performance Evaluation
Corporation spec generated these workloads.
And this is a equation to truth table workloads, equal thought, let's say.
And you can see that this was one of the most difficult branches to predict until processor
designers started to put global branch predictors into their machines.
So here, for example, if B1 this branch is taken and B2 is taken, then B 3 is not taken, right?
Because there are some data dependencies that are set as you can see, right?
You can convince yourself again, only a global branch predictor can actually do this nicely.
OK, so how do you capture this global branch correlation in hardware?
The idea is very simple, basically similar to what I just described right?
You associate branch outcomes with a global taken not taken history TN or 01 taken as one, usually
10 history of all branches, and make a prediction based on the outcome of the branch the last time
the same global branch history was encountered.
So you have a global branch history register that keeps track of the taken not taken outcome of the
last N branches.
N could be.
4IN Pentium proton was 4.
In today's machines it's up to 16, even even higher actually, as we will see thousands sometimes,
but that's a different type of prediction mechanism, as we will see.
But this exploits this global branch history.
Still.
You see in this global branch history once, and you predict the branch as taken and it was correct.
The next time you see the exact history, you'll predict as taken and hopefully you'll be correct
again.
If this predictability is actually pretty strong, this correlation is strong.
That's the idea basically.
So implementation, I've given you a kind of implementation.
Also keep track of the global TN taken, not taken, history of all branches and the register all
branches, all recent branches.
It's clear that's the register that's of limited size.
This is called the global history register or global register, Some people call it.
Use this global history register to index into a table that records the outcome or that recorded the
outcome that was seen for each GHR value in the recent past.
This is called pattern history table.
Table of two bit counters basically.
So instead of indexing a table of two bit counters with just a program counter, we're going to index
it with a global history register, right?
We'll still have the hysteresis.
This is called the global history or global branch predictor.
Basically you, the reason it's called also a 2 levels of history is you're, you're using 2 levels of
history.
One's the global history of all branches, and the other is history that you've seen at that point
for that global history in the past, right?
We're not using program counter.
Remember, program counter is not part of this equation right now, OK?
This is what the implementation looks like.
This is our global history register.
And let's assume that this has four bits.
These are the four previous branches.
This is the most recent previous branch.
This is the fourth most recent, the oldest branch that you've seen that you could accommodate in
your global history register.
So it's N bits, the directions of last N branches, essentially global history.
You use this to index into two bit counters like what we have seen earlier.
It could be also one bit counter, but we're going to use the 2 bit counters so that we keep
hysteresis.
This is a table of saturating counters for each history entry.
And this gives you the direction the branch to the last time the same history was seen, except it's
not the same branch potentially, right?
Because we're using history, we're not using program counter.
So there is some interference that happens because of this.
We can fix this problem later on, but we're going to talk about that.
So this works actually surprisingly well because it exploits some program behaviour.
And these are two bit counters, as you see.
So 2 levels of history, history one and then history, history at that.
History.
OK, so the, the paper that I assigned to you, which is a very influential technical report, this was
never published anywhere, but it was actually a technical report by Digital Equipment Corporation,
Western Research Laboratory.
Scott MacFarlane did a lot of research on branch predictors and he wrote this paper where he
described how some of these things work.
And I like his example.
For example, if you look at these two loops, there's one branch that test J, that's the inner loop.
There's one branch that test I, that's the outer loop, right?
And you know that the results are taken, taken, not taken over here.
And the first one is usually taken, right?
Almost always taken.
So this branch test I, this red branch, let's start with that outer loop, last three branches before
this test J, right?
And the history is always taken taken, not taken for the last three branches.
And this is the earlier branch that tested I previously in the previous iteration.
So that's also taken, right?
If you've gone to this place, it must have been taken, right?
So the history that you see at this branch is always TTTN at the global register.
Taken, taken, taken, taken, not taken.
Yeah.
So you predict taken for that eye branch because it's a loop branch, right?
It's mostly taken, right.
So you shift in the next history, meaning you drop out the oldest one and you put in the newest one.
So the history becomes taken, taken, not taken, taken, which is essentially taken, taken, not taken,
taken over here.
And whenever you see that history, the results is taken, right?
Because you're at that branch kind of.
And then you shift in that and the global history becomes like this 1011 again, the result and the
prediction is taken.
So this is one reason why one, one example that shows how a global history predictor works.
And you can read it if you're interested.
There are a lot of good Nuggets here.
OK, OK, so this was actually implemented right away in the Intel Pentium Pro branch predictor.
It's A2 level global branch predictor, so it has four bit global history register.
It's very small compared to today's predictors, but it has also multiple pattern history tables of
two bit counters.
Basically which pattern history table you use is the.
Determined by lower order bits of the branch address.
So they use a global history to index into one of the pattern history tables 2 bit counters.
And which 2 bit counters you index depends on the program counter a little bit.
So there's some differentiation based on the program counter also, so that not all branches
basically you, you basically try to use the program counter as context information to actually
decide how to predict a branch as well.
And this is the first widely commercially successful auto order execution machine.
It has all the concepts that we talked about auto order execution, superscalar execution, 2 level
branch prediction, global and precise exceptions using reorder buffer.
And it's basically the predecessor of all of these machines that are out here that are much bigger
right now.
OK, and that's Intel Pentium Pro.
OK, So this was our one level branch predictor you have, we indexed the direction predictor with the
program counter.
If you remember, the two level branch predictor looks like this.
Basically we don't use the program counter, but we use the global branch history register.
But you can have multiple direction predictor tables and you select which one to use based on some
bits of the program counter.
For example.
You could also do that.
That's what Pentium Pro did.
All good.
Fascinating, right?
Yes.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely.
I mean, Penteon Pro is probably one of the most successful processors of its time.
Yeah, it was a revolution and it was partially enabled by this branch predictor.
OK, OK.
So how do you improve global predictor accuracy?
I'll give you one other idea.
Essentially add more context information.
Intel did this in Pentium Pro with some way as we discussed, right?
You decide which pattern history table to use based on some program counter bits, but you can also
do it in some other way in a cheaper way.
You take into account which bank is being predicted.
This is called the G share predictor and the idea is to take the global history register and hash it
with the branch PC and that gives you more information about the branch you're predicting.
Looks like this.
You have the branch address program counter.
You have the branch history register.
You use a hash function which may be XOR.
You can have better hash functions but then they increase your latency potentially and then you
index into the pattern history table.
This turns out it gives you better prediction accuracy compared to just using branch history
register, global history register.
There are two reasons.
One is you use more context information for the prediction itself.
You take into account program counter because there are benefits to that also, as we can guess.
And you also better utilise the two bit counter array because if you actually use only history, some
histories, some, some parts of the array become hotter than others.
And if you're actually hashing using some other information, you better utilise the array.
So not everything maps to the same place.
OK, there's a lot more analysis of this than many other papers that I'm not going to talk about.
The downside of course whenever you use this sort of hashing is to increase your latency.
XOR is not that bad, but some other hashing functions may be bad.
OK, so this is what it looks like basically in my pictures.
You have global history, you have program counter, you use a hash function and then you index the
direction predictor.
On top of this, you may index different direction predictors with different PCs also.
So there is a lot of design space that people have explored in this and there are many papers
there's an on this topic.
OK, the question is, can we do better than this?
Let's go to the second realisation.
Second realisation is local branch correlation.
Essentially a branch is correlated with itself and we're going to try to exploit that beyond what a
2 bit counter can provide.
So this is again from the paper that I suggested.
So if you look at this loop branch, it's very predictable, right?
I'm going to read this.
Actually, if the loop test is done at the end of the body for this loop, the corresponding branch
will execute the pattern 1110 to the end, which is taken, taken, taken, not taken, where one and
zero represent taken and not taken, respectively, and N is the number of times the loop is
executed.
Clearly, if he knew the direction this branch had gone on the previous three executions, then we
could always be able to predict the next branch direction.
So you can think about that a little bit.
And that's true.
Basically, you keep repeating the same pattern, right?
So this is how it works for that particular 1110 and pattern.
So this is the history of the branch 1110 it's predicted taken and then you shifting something 1101
history, it's predicted taken again.
1011 it's predicted taken again.
The only time it's predicted not taken is 0111.
The last history is 0111 and you can guess why again, right, 0111.
The next one will be 0, right?
OK, so basically what happens is if you have a branch predictor that keeps track of, let's say the
last four iterations of the branch, you map that local history to different 2 bit counters, right?
And that enables you to distinguish the different iterations of the loop.
And this gives you a better predictability in this particular example, right?
There could be other examples.
So that's the idea.
By having a separate pattern history table entry for each local history, we can distinguish
different iterations of a loop.
This works for short loops.
If the loops are long, like a million times iterating, this may not work, but you may not care
anyway because hopefully you're going to predict those loops with almost perfect accuracy, right?
That's the idea.
Short loops are harder.
OK, so how do you capture this?
I've shown you an example of this, but we have a per branch history register.
Associate the predicted outcome of a branch with the taken not taken history of the same branch.
For every branch you have a history register and make a prediction based on the outcome of the
branch the last time the same local history was encountered.
This is called the local history predictor or local branch predictor and it's again uses 2 levels of
history.
The first level is the per branch history register, the second level is the history at that history
register value.
2 bit counters basically.
Second level is always 2 bit counters.
I like thinking of it that way.
It could be 3 bits also, or one bit.
So the picture looks kind of similar.
But now our local history registers are a bit more expensive, right?
The idea is a set of local history registers.
Each of them are M bits.
M bits are how many of the same branch you have kept track of in terms of history.
And you choose which local history register to use based on the program counter of the branch.
So you index this table using the program counter.
Every time you see the same program counter, it maps to the same entry and that gives you the local
history that you've seen for that program counter.
And you use that local history to index the pattern history table.
Basically that's the idea.
Pattern history table, maybe one or many.
Again, I'm going to actually generalise this later on.
So the second level is very similar to what we've seen.
It's a table of saturating counters for each history entry.
And you have the.
Basically they store the direction the branch took the last time the same history was seen, right?
So the only difference between local and global history is which history do you use?
In global history register, we had a single history register where all branches contributed to it.
Here we have a per branch history register.
Again, per branch is hard to implement clearly.
If you have a million branches in your program, do you have a million entries?
No.
So what you do is you do some sort of hashing.
Some branches will map to the same history register.
Hopefully they won't destroy each other's accuracy, but this is a real problem and people analyse
this problem for with many works they try to reduce that effect.
OK, so this is what the local history branch predictor looks like.
Using the program counter you pick a local history register, so which takes time.
Now this is a longer latency process.
And then you use the local history register to index into the direction predictor pattern history
tables and each Register here provides which directions early instance of this branch went.
OK, OK, so there's a generalisation of this in the original paper.
I'll go through this relatively quickly, but essentially branch history registry can be global or it
could be for per set of branches.
Based on some program counter you decide a global history.
Or it could be per branch.
Pattern history table counters can be adaptive or static.
Adaptive means you have two bit counters.
Static means compiler decides what to do.
That's very difficult to do.
Nobody uses static as far as I know.
And pattern history table can be global, basically used by all branches, or they can be used per
different set of branches based on the program counter.
Or they could be per branch, which is very hard to implement anyway, right?
So this is the global predictor.
The branch history register is global.
The pattern history table is global, shared across all branches.
There is no program counter involvement let's say and you have pattern history counters that are
adaptive, meaning 2 bit counters.
This is the cheapest version, let's say global, and this is the most expensive version.
Everything is per branch and you can see that there's a huge design space over here and with hashing
functions, design space increases.
Sounds good.
OK, so if you're interested, you can read the retrospective of this paper on two level adaptive
training branch prediction where they talk about how they came up with it, etcetera.
The question of course we ask is, is this the end?
Can we do better?
Right.
And we can.
Basically, there are many ideas that people have developed and it turns out.
One idea doesn't fit all meaning.
Global history is good for some branches.
Local history is good for some other branches.
Predictably, all of branches varies.
I already said all of this.
For some others, a simple 2 bit counter is enough, because they don't really require history right?
They're basically stand alone.
They check some value and they're not really dependent that much on the program path, for example.
For yet others, a single bit is enough, right?
For some others, even static prediction is enough.
Right for meaning always taken for example, that says a single bit, I guess.
So basically the observation is that there is heterogeneity in the predictability behaviour of
branches.
No one-size-fits-all branch prediction algorithm.
So we the idea is to exploit that heterogeneity by designing heterogeneous predictors.
Whenever you see different behaviour, a good design principle is to think hybrid or heterogeneous
and we're going to do exactly that.
So hybrid branch predictors, which is first introduced by MacFarlane that technical report, use more
than one type of predictor, multiple algorithms to select the best and then select the best
prediction.
Now you're faced with a choice that's that's selecting the best predictor.
How do you select the best prediction becomes an issue, right?
So for example, you can have a hybrid of two bit counters and global predictor.
The advantages, let's talk about the events and we'll talk about some examples of this, but you get
better accuracy.
Basically, different predictors are better for different branches as long as you're choosing the
right predictor for the branch.
There is another advantage which is reduced warm up time.
We did not discuss this much, but faster warm up predictor can be used until the slower warm up
predictor warms up.
So if you think about a long history, if your history is 16 previous branches, it takes time to
actually populate that history, right?
Local history becomes even harder to populate potentially if you have lots of local histories,
etcetera.
So you may use a 2 bit counter prediction until that predictor warms up, right?
So larger tables are harder to warm up.
This is in general true.
And if you don't have a table you use a single bit, then it's much easier.
OK, there are other.
There are also disadvantages.
Now you need to have a meta predictor or selector or choice predictor to decide which predictor to
use.
You have longer access latency because you make choices, right?
There's at least a Max, as you will see.
So there's more hardware and complexity, but this is well warranted.
Every branch predictor that you have in your pockets or anywhere is a hybrid predictor today, and it
may look like this.
This is from 1990s alpha 21 to 64 microprocessor, which was the biggest competitor to a Pentium Pro.
And they also designed an out of order machine with some similar mechanisms, except their branch
predictor was much better.
And I'll give you some real parameters from that machine.
The minimum branch penalty was 7 cycles.
Typical branch penalty was 11 cycles.
That's the misprediction penalty.
They use a target address cache inside the instruction cache, and they reset the predictor tables
when the process switched.
We're going to talk about processes later on, but it's good to think about how do these things
change with different when different programs are executed.
But let's take a look at this predictor.
This predictor is essentially, you can see that there's a global history over here of 12 bits, and
there's a global predictor 2 to the 12 entries.
Each of them is 2 bits, 2 bit counters.
You can see there is a local history table indexed by the program counter, and each history is 10
bit long.
And you have a local predictor that's essentially 2 to the 10 entries and each has three bits SO3
bits saturating counters.
Basically that's what they decided to do based on whatever decisions they made.
So local predictor gives you a local prediction, global predictor gives you a global prediction.
And then there's a choice predictor over here that decides which one was better.
And that is, it turns out, according to them, at least according to this picture at least, they use
the global history to the site.
Basically, there's a separate choice predictor that gets trained which predictor has done better at
this particular global history in the past using some hysteresis.
And then they choose, OK, and this is better than any other predictor, including the global
predictor that's used in Pentium Pro because it uses more information, more hardware.
So now you can also see that there's a multiplexer over here that makes things longer latency.
OK, OK, So there are also other ideas people have developed.
One is bias branches and branch filtering.
That's a very good idea actually.
In general, classify your branches and do as much work as the branch needs, right?
If the branch doesn't need a sophisticated prediction algorithm, don't use a sophisticated
prediction algorithm.
That's going to be one of the principles that is going to be used in a lot of these techniques.
And it turns out many branches are biased in One Direction.
There are some branches that are 99% taken right.
You don't need the sophisticated machinery for them.
There are multiple reasons.
One is you're wasting hardware.
The second is you're polluting the branch prediction structures that could be used.
For something that really requires the hardware to get better accuracy, right?
Basically you make the prediction of other branches difficult by causing interference in the branch
prediction tables and in history registers.
That's the idea.
If you can somehow remove these branches, meaning detect such biased branches and predict them with
a simpler predictor like last time or static predictor, you can do much better.
And a lot of processors do this actually.
They detect which branches are easily predictable using different types of methods, either using
some sort of profiling, dynamic profiling, using some counters, or they look at the counters,
etcetera.
And this paper is the one that's that introduced this idea.
Sounds good, right?
It makes sense, actually.
A lot of things make sense, but over time things got developed better.
So the question is, are we done right?
So you do all of these and you get maybe 90 to 97% prediction accuracy on average.
Unfortunately, some difficult workloads suffer.
Not all workloads have this.
Some workloads are still at 50%, maybe 40%.
For example.
Compilers are usually very difficult to predict.
GCC compiler, if you're executing that, it's very difficult to predict the branches inside there.
So these are some old numbers.
Maximum IPC with tournament prediction is 9, whereas if you have perfect prediction, IPC can be 35
according to some results.
So that's why people keep developing branch predictors and there's actually a championship branch
prediction coming up.
If you're so inclined.
You can actually think new ideas and submit and who knows, maybe you'll win.
I'll have a link over there on the on the slide soon.
But let me give you some more recent ideas as well, right?
So the ideas are actually very interesting.
One is loop branches.
You can actually do better with these.
The other is using machine learning and the other is using actually sophisticated hybrid history
length.
So the loop branches essentially.
If you can detect a loop iteration count, maybe you don't need to use a predictor using histories
right you the guess is going to be this loop is going to iterate 5 times.
Assuming that's stable, you can actually do a much better prediction.
That's the idea over here.
This works well for loops with small number of iterations where iteration count is predictable.
This way you actually do remove those loops from the prediction structures other prediction
structures.
This is used in Intel Pentium M perceptron.
How many people know about perceptrons here?
OK, that's good.
These are single layer neural networks.
Let's say they're not networks, they're really perceptrons.
But you these learn the direction correlations between individual branches and assign weights to
correlations using simple machine learning.
I'm going to cover this if we have time.
This was introduced in 2001 and it's essentially in many processors today also.
And the third idea is to have hybrid history length.
Some branches are predictable with short history lengths.
Some branches require very long history lengths because they may be correlated with some other part
of the program that you executed ages ago, right?
How do you actually capture both history lengths and classify which branches should be predicted
with what kind of history lengths, right?
This is going to, and this is a very clever idea, basically have tables that have history lengths
that are part of a geometric function, right?
So some mystery lengths are small, but some mystery lengths are very long.
And then you manage the tables to decide which branch should be predicted by which table.
And this is called the tage predictor.
And again, it's even more popular than the perceptron wrench predictor.
A lot of high performance processors, including these things are based on the tage predictor right
now.
OK, let's take a look at the loop and jump predictors.
I'm not going to talk about the jump predictor.
These are indirect predictors.
I have some backup slides if you're interested, but this is a loop predictor.
For example, somehow you identify how many iteration counts you will have in a loop, that's called
the limit.
And every time you execute the branch, you increment the count, then check it compared to the limits
and if the count reaches the limit, your prediction will be not taken.
You mean you go out of the loop?
Otherwise your prediction will be taken.
This works well if you can identify these branches that are predictable using same iteration counts
in the past.
OK.
And if you look at INTEMP and two M advanced branch prediction is a good part of the chip.
This is Intel's picture, so I'm hoping that they got it right, although you never know, but it's a
substantial part of the processor actually with branch prediction structures, not as much as
memory, but substantial.
And branch prediction also has a lot of memory in it.
So OK, so let's talk about some of these more advanced prediction mechanisms that are employed in
existing processors.
Perceptrons.
So perceptrons were developed in 1950s.
Essentially, the idea was to have a simplified model of a biological neuron, right?
It's an artificial neuron, and today's neural networks are all artificial neural networks, and
they're all started from perceptron basically.
It's also a simple binary classifier.
Basically, a perceptron maps an input vector.
X to a zero or one.
I'm going to put this into the branch prediction context soon.
Input is a vector of X.
It could be a vector of words, for example.
And perceptron learns the linear function, if one exists, of how each element of the vector affects
the output stored in an internal weight vector.
And you may multiply this with the probability of each word being in a language, for example.
And you see a set of words and you basically multiply it with some weights.
And then the you train it in some way such that this can tell you whether the words belong to
English with some likelihood, right?
It's a binary classifier.
So English or not English, German or not German, whatever.
But we're going to apply it to the context of branch prediction.
So this is the computation that we're going to do.
You have the vector X that is the input, and then you have a vector of weights which store the
correlations.
And then there's some bias.
You may set it to 0 if you don't want any bias, but for bias branches it's actually quite useful.
And the output is whether that computation is greater than 0.
So in the branch prediction context, vector X is the branch history register bits taken, not taken.
1 zeros, right?
That's the global history register.
Assume that this is global history.
Right now output is a prediction for the current branch.
Now you can actually train the weights to figure out which bits in the global history register are
positively or negatively correlated with the outcome of the current branch.
That's the idea, right?
So a little bit more detail.
We would like to use a perceptron to learn the correlations between branch history register bits.
These are the XS over here and the branch outcome.
So a perceptron learns the target Boolean function of N inputs over here.
These are the N inputs that you have.
And then the bias over here.
Each branch is associated with a perceptron.
You can think of it that way.
Of course, there could be aliasing, but in the best case, each branch is associated with a
perceptron.
A perceptron contains a set of weights WI.
These are the weights over here.
So you store these set of weights with the perceptron based on the PC program counter, and each
weight corresponds to a bit in the global history register.
So this bit in the global history register is correlated with this branch using this weight.
It represents how much that bit is correlated with the direction of the branch, right?
For example, if you have positive correlation, you have a large positive weight based on what you've
seen in the past, you keep updating the weights and if you have a negative correlation, you'll have
a large negative weight.
That's the idea.
And this is the function that we're going to compute.
Basically we we do a vector multiplication or dot product computation, we're going to multiply the
branch history register bits with the correlated weights associated with the current branch that
we're fetching.
That's the multiplication over here, and we're going to add a bias bit, and that's our output.
If that output is greater than some threshold, we're going to say the branch is predicted taken.
Otherwise it's predicted not taken, right?
So that sounds nice, right?
It's very, the key is learning those weights, of course.
So how do you do the prediction?
Express global history registers as one taken and -1 in this case, 0 doesn't work, unfortunately,
because you need to do positive and negative not taken.
You take a dot product of the global history register and the weights, as I said, if the output is
greater than 0, you predict the branch has taken.
Sounds nice, expensive because you have a dot product computation right?
Now for every branch, you're fetching the branch you want to predict what's the next?
What is the direction?
And you have a matrix, not matrix dot product multiplication, right?
If you can do it in one cycle, that's good, but you didn't do other stuff also, right?
So it's not easy to implement in a single cycle.
OK.
That's why people developed a lot of pipelining mechanisms that I'm not going to talk about how to
make it work.
So this is the prediction function.
Let me go into this over here, you have the branch address program counter.
You index a table of perceptrons and you select the perceptron that maps to that particular branch.
These are essentially the weights.
And then you have the global history register.
You basically multiply the global history register with the perceptron and compute Y.
And then the prediction is over here.
And then there's a training part, which I will not go into, but you update the weights to account
for the correlation.
Basically, if both branches are taken, you increment the weights.
If board branches are not taken, you decrement the associated weight, basically.
OK, There's also a bias weight.
This is the bias of the branch independent of the history.
There's a way of setting it.
So if the branch is really truly biased, you basically bias it to be taken or not taken using this
weight.
And you can also train that.
OK.
I think I've shown all of these over here.
So what is the advantage and this advantage of this, the big advantage is it's a more sophisticated
learning mechanism, right?
And it directly leads to better accuracy when this was first published in 2001.
I was doing my PhD and I was working on some prefetching mechanisms called run at execution, which
we may cover later on a little bit.
And I said I need a better branch predictor because my mechanism was important, needed better branch
prediction accuracy.
And I immediately implemented this thing in the paper and it immediately worked.
I got 20% better accuracy and my mechanism became better also.
So it's good.
Basically it works.
So it enables also Long Branch history lengths because you're doing actually a multiplication across
very long lengths potentially it gives you better accuracy at the cost of multiplication, of
course, right dot product computation, OK, this advantage is complexity, meaning adder tree to
compute the perceptron output, right, that multiplication and then also comparison.
So this is not simple.
Basically in the end, previously we were doing table look UPS, we weren't doing any computation.
Now we're doing computation to predict a branch, right?
So it's expensive in terms of energy complexity, hardware area, a lot of things.
Of course, it has the downsides of perceptrons.
Perceptrons, unfortunately, it cannot learn X or functions, for example, linearly inseparable
functions.
I'm not going to go through this in detail, but every machine learning mechanism has self some
potential downside.
Perceptrons being a single layer and being based operating the way we discussed, they cannot learn
all functions.
You can make this better by having multi layer perceptrons, which complicates the mechanism.
You can make this better by having neural networks, which makes the mechanism even more complex.
Right.
We're going to talk about that maybe later on.
Yeah, I think I've said this.
It cannot learn extra type of correlation between two history bits and branch outcome, for example.
But despite all of these disadvantages, a successful example of use of machine learning in hardware
in processor design today, things are changing.
There is more stuff that's being proposed using machine learning, but this was the first, one of the
first successful use of machine learning in processor design in something as critical as branch
prediction.
OK, so for example, Samsung designed this processor Xenos.
You can read about that.
They employ, they employ A perceptron predictor.
AMD also employs perceptron predictors.
I don't know if they still employ, but in some, some of these processors they do employ.
And you can see also some pictures that basically describe how these operate on AMD chips.
OK, let me give you another idea, which is a competitor which doesn't have one of some of the
downsides, but which doesn't use machine learning also.
And some of there's some overlap in the predictability of the branches.
I think in the end the two approaches can be combined also and people are looking into that.
But let me give you the idea and then you can think about it.
Maybe the idea is to use multiple history lengths.
And I've already given you the idea.
Basically, different branches require different history lengths for better prediction accuracy.
Some require very few history bits because they're correlated with a close by branch.
Some require thousands of history bits because they're correlated with some branch that was executed
a long time ago.
Right?
And the idea is to have multiple pH TS, better history tables indexed with global history registers
with different history lengths and intelligently decide which one to use, intelligently allocate
pattern history table entries, 2 bit counters, basically two different branches in different
tables.
So it kind of looks like this.
It looks complicated, but it's not that bad actually.
So there's one predictor that's very simple.
You use just the program counter.
It doesn't need any history.
For example, there's another predictor that requires a small history.
So history length over here is something but small.
There's another predictor that that follows.
Large history.
Longer history, longer history, right?
And this is a geometric series.
You can make a different series, etcetera.
But the history over here may be 4 bits, the history over here may be 1000 bits, right?
That's the idea, OK.
And the key is basically deciding which predictor to use, because if you actually pollute all the
predictors with the same branch, this is going to be very expensive, right?
So there are some algorithms that decide which predictors are best and the branches get allocated to
those different tables.
I'm not going to go into that, but this is the basic idea.
There's a lot of optimization that needs to be done over here.
So it kind of looks like this.
You have, for example, this can be better predicted with a small amount of history, large amount of
history, and longer amount of history, right?
That's the idea.
So the advantages, if you can choose the best history length to predict each branch, you can get a
better accuracy.
And this is actually proven also with another predictor that works.
It enables Long Branch history lengths in a much more feasible way than perceptron, right?
If you want thousand history lengths, you have a small table, and you're very careful in which
branches go to that small table with perceptron if you want to have 1000.
Bits you need to have 1000 bits in the weight vector and that's expensive and that makes the
multiplication tree also bad, you know, so disadvantageous Hardware design complexity is not low,
probably lower than the perceptron.
This could be more easily accommodated in the cycle time you need to.
The downside is there is some black magic that you need to figure out, meaning you need to choose
good hash functions and table sizes and update policies to maximise accuracy and minimise latency.
And there's another successful recent idea that is used in many modern Prostor designs, including
AMD Zen, which uses perceptron at one level and tage another level.
So you can see there is this L1 hash perceptron over here and there's tage somewhere else.
Yeah, yeah, new tage bench predictor they add.
Anyway, L2 over here.
OK.
And this is kind of the AM DS tage predictor, but you can take a look at it more.
OK, so why does this work?
Essentially, different branch branches are correlated with different branches, right?
That's the idea over here.
And it's good to analyse this once in a while.
And I think this analysis needs to be done.
Unfortunately, I don't see a lot of work to really understand things these days.
There's this beautiful paper again from my advisor and one of his students where they showed they
analysed a lot of programs at the time in 1990s, and they showed that if you want to predict a
branch very accurately, there are only three past branches, maximum three, that really matter for
you.
The problem is those 3 branches can be anywhere.
For some branches, they're close by, for some branches they're far away, and for some branches
they're all over the place.
So if you can somehow magically identify 3 branches, that really enable you to predict this branch
more accurately.
So there's a lot of opportunity.
It could be an idea to start the championship branch prediction with if you're so inclined.
OK, the question is always can we do better?
Right.
And we're going to do better.
This is the state-of-the-art in branch Prediction, at least published branch prediction.
This is from Andre Sesnick, who's the developer of TH Predictors.
I will not go through this in detail again, but the main ideas are all there.
You can see there's global, local.
There's also something like skeleton that I will not go into.
There's the main TH predictor, which is based on some global history and program counter.
And there's also some confidence which we will discuss how confident are you in your prediction?
If you're not confident, then you use some other stuff and there's some statistical analysis that
this predictor does.
And then there's a loop predictor over here.
So you can see that there is a huge hybrid mechanism over here and loop predictor is not gone.
It's still important, you know, if you can get get rid of the loops easily, get rid of the loops
easily.
So this is a sophisticated predictor.
It's the, it's the one that won the championship branch prediction about 10 years ago.
And you can take a look at it.
Some other ideas.
People have used convolutional neural networks in branch prediction more recently.
This is very hard to do, I think especially dynamically.
The idea is to use it for hard to predict branches, especially if you know that a branch is really,
really hard to predict, try to use something much more sophisticated, right?
So that's the idea over here.
I will not go through this in detail, but this users Commission neural network predictor for very
hard to predict branches and users stage SCL, which is this thing for everything else.
So you can see that people actually people cannot get rid of the previous thing because they
actually designed for many different types of branches, right?
OK, but maybe you'll get rid of it, I don't know.
So branch confidence estimation, I should also talk about this.
This basically idea is estimate if the prediction is likely to be correct, estimate how confident
you are in the prediction.
Basically, why do you want to do this?
Well, it could be very useful in deciding how to speculate, right?
For example, which predictor to use, which pattern history table to use, whether to keep fetching on
this path, whether whether to switch to some other thread or program?
Yeah, whether to switch to some other way of handling the branch, right?
For example, if you've fetched 5 low confident branches in your pipeline and you can basically guess
that you may be on the wrong path, right?
And if you're on the wrong path, maybe you stop fetching to save energy.
Wrong path is not necessarily useful useless, but it's more being on the correct path is more likely
useful than being on the wrong path, right?
OK, I mean the the reason I say wrong path is not necessarily useless is because you may actually be
pre fetching some data on the wrong path.
We'll get back to that later on.
OK, So this is an example of how to estimate confidence, keep a record of correct incorrect outcomes
of past and instance of the branch based on those patterns, guess if the current prediction will
likely be correct or incorrect, OK.
And there are many confidence estimation because including.
Based mechanisms that people have developed, this is separate from the branch prediction by the way.
You have a branch prediction mechanism and you have a confidence estimation mechanism.
And confidence estimation mechanism enables you to do better branch prediction and also maybe not
doing branch prediction and doing something else right.
And one application is pipeline gating.
And I've already given you the idea if you have more low confidence branches than a threshold in
your machine, stop fetching from that threat.
Save energy, for example.
OK, so are we done with branch prediction?
And the idea is, no.
This was the last branch prediction competition in 2025.
You can look at the results of this, but if you're interested, there's another one coming up.
The submission deadline is May 8th.
So if you have very good ideas on branch prediction, maybe you can win.
And maybe your idea can go into all of the major microprostors.
OK, we're going to stop here.
I'll see you tomorrow.